IGF-1. Do you ever use IGF-1 uh in your
clinic? Does it have a place in the HRT
business?
>> We don't prescribe IGF-1 LR3 because it
is heavily scrutinized and we try to
keep a clean operation. We try to take
care of patients from a health first
perspective while also staying within
various guidelines of FDA and other
regulatory agencies. And I feel we can
do a good job as we have both making
patients happy and healthier while also
maintaining um a clean line of you know
lensure and and and and keeping
regulators happy. So we don't use that
particular peptide. What we do use is we
use other IGF-1
or growth hormone secrets like Samorin
which is FDA approved for humans. We use
tessamorin which is very similar to
samorin has a better affinity for
visceral fat reduction. Uh it does tend
to be a little pricier than samorin
which is why both options are very
viable. Both of those do a great job
with IGF-1. Um and and they are safer
than a lot of the other things out
there. Um testosterone in and of itself
generally tends to raise IGF-1 levels as
well. So when a man initiates TRT and
it's done correctly and managed
correctly, you'll notice an upswing in
IGF-1 over time as well, even in the
absence of any uh IGF analog or secret
and sleep quality sleep will help IGF-1
as well and a reduction in in car
carbohydrates. So it's not your opinion
that every man 45 50 that is already
optimized on testosterone should also
explore using GH or an analog.
>> I I I'm very cautious in using the word
every man because when you make a
blanket statement like that you're
encompassing everyone and you're taking
away the ability to assess people as
individuals. saying every man know there
are contra indications to IGF-1
elevations for example the known
presence of cancer right we know that
cancer is proliferated with an increase
in IGF-1 and uh if someone has uh known
and present cancer then obviously it's
contraindicated if someone is a type 2
diabetic or insulin resistant or
pre-diabetic or has an elevated A1C or
elevated fasted sugar or elevated
insulin levels all of those things may
potentially be contraindicated for IGF-1
therapy so to say every man abs
Absolutely not to say a lot of men can
benefit from it. Yes. Considering all of
these conditions have been discussed,
assessed and taken into account before
issuing a prescription.
>> Mhm. Uh if I remember correctly, you do
prefer uh secrets above HGH, right?
>> Absolutely. We have never and never will
prescribe recumbent human growth hormone
because when you prescribe an exogenous
hormone much like we do with
testosterone, we know that there's a
couple of things that occur. First and
foremost, you have suppression and that
suppression with testosterone is fine
because you are suppressing something
that is already deficient and presumably
needs to be replaced indefinitely. when
you're suppressing growth hormone,
considering the fact that there are much
bigger risks and significant side effect
profiles and contraindications that tes
the generally does not have and it's
significantly a you know very pricey
endeavor. This is not something you want
to do forever and you don't want to
suppress someone's ability to release
growth hormone out of their pituitary
because if that condition becomes
irreversible or becomes deficient to an
extent in the future where they're
dependent on this ex exogenous
medication, you're relegating them to a
position where they may not be able to
get that medication due to cost
prohibition, due to regulatory issues or
due to side effect profile issues that
make it a contra indication. And if any
of those conditions exist, this
individual is now in a world of trouble.
So I don't like them for that reason,
coupled by the fact that from a
regulatory standpoint, they are heavily
scrutinized. So secrets are
significantly safer and you don't run
all of those risks, including acromegaly
and cardomegaly and you know uh uh uh
progressing type 2 diabetes and
progressing existing cancers. All things
that are significantly less uh profound
with a secret gut compared to a a uh
synthetic uh uh exogenous uh growth
hormone.